<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="1">
<l n="1">Beginning to chant the earth and broad sea, and the rivers</l>
<l n="2">and cities, and endless tribes of men, </l>
<l n="3">I will commemorate the deep-flowing Ocean. For within it </l>
<l n="4">the whole land, as an immense island, is crowned,</l>
<l n="5">not however completely circular throughout, but separately</l>
<l n="6">becoming more pointed towards the sun's paths,</l>
<l n="7">resembling a sling; and although it is one, </l>
<l n="8">people have divided it into three continents:</l>
<l n="9">first Libya, and then Europe, and Asia.</l>
<l n="10">Well, then, Libya has a slanting division from Europe,</l>
<l n="11">along the line "Gadeira and the mouth of the Neilos",</l>
<l n="12">where lies the northernmost creek of Aegyptus,</l>
<l n="13">and the well-known sacred precinct of Amyclaean Canobus;</l>
<l n="14">and Europe from Asia divides the Tanais, through the middle,</l>
<l n="15">which then winding through the land of the Sauromatae</l>
<l n="16">sweeps into Scythia and into the lake Maeotis,</l>
<l n="17">towards the north; and in the south the boundary is the Hellespontus.</l>
<l n="18">This boundary-mark is stretched further south into the mouth of the Neilos.</l>
<l n="19">But others then separate continents through the land.</l>
<l n="20">A certain isthmus stretches above, uppermost in the Asian land,</l>
<l n="21">between the Caspian and the Euxine seas;</l>
<l n="22">this they have called the boundary of Europe and Asia;</l>
<l n="23">Another again, long and unutterable, creeps into the south,</l>
<l n="24">between the Arabian gulf and Aegyptus,</l>
<l n="25">which then separates Libya from the Asian land.</l>
<l n="26">Such have mortals proclaimed concerning boundaries;</l>
<l n="27">but on all sides flows the might of tireless Ocean,</l>
<l n="28">and being one, yet endowed with many names:</l>
<l n="29">well, by the furthest recess of the Locrian zephyr</l>
<l n="30">it is called the Western Atlas, but above,</l>
<l n="31">towards the north, where dwell the children of the war-mad Arimaspoi,</l>
<l n="32">they call it the Frozen and the Cronion Sea;</l>
<l n="33">others, again, called it also the Dead, because of the weakness</l>
<l n="34">of the sun; with a dim light shines it over that sea,</l>
<l n="35">and it is always blunted in dark clouds;</l>
<l n="36">but where the sun first appears to people,</l>
<l n="37">they call the wave of the sea Eastern and Indian;</l>
<l n="38">nearby they call it the Erythraean, and the Aethiopian</l>
<l n="39">towards the south, where there a large curve of uninhabited land</l>
<l n="40">extends, burnt by the sun's fierce rays.</l>
<l n="41">Thus Ocean encompasses the whole earth,</l>
<l n="42">being such and bearing among people such names.</l>
<l n="43">Here and there it belches gulfs, casting itself inwards </l>
<l n="44">into a sea, many small, and four very large ones;</l>
<l n="45">So, then, the foremost one is, which begets the Western Sea,</l>
<l n="46">sweeping from Libya into the Pamphylian land;</l>
<l n="47">and the second one is small but excelling the others,</l>
<l n="48">which, spreading from the Cronion Sea out of the north,</l>
<l n="49">sends forth a lofty stream into the Caspian Sea,</l>
<l n="50">which others also the Hyrcanian called.</l>
<l n="51">Of the others gulfs, which are both from the southern sea, </l>
<l n="52">one is higher, pouring forth the Persian wave,</l>
<l n="53">turned opposite the Caspian Sea;</l>
<l n="54">and the other, the Arabian gulf, swells within, </l>
<l n="55">winding its channel to the south of the Pontus Euxinus.</l>
<l n="56">So many are gulfs of deep-waved Ocean,</l>
<l n="57">the greater ones, but there are countless others.</l>
<l n="58">And now I will tell of the path of the Western sea, which</l>
<l n="59">wanders to and from all the continents with its oblique waves, </l>
<l n="60">sometimes encircling islands, and sometimes in turn</l>
<l n="61">brushing below the feet of mountains or cities.</l>
<l n="62">And you, o Muses, tell of crooked ways</l>
<l n="63">beginning in order from the Western Ocean:</l>
<l n="64">there by the boundaries also the pillars of Heracles</l>
<l n="65">stand, a great wonder, beside outermost Gadeira,</l>
<l n="66">under the broad slopes of the wide-spread Atlantes,</l>
<l n="67">where also a bronze column runs into heaven, </l>
<l n="68">tall, and covered by dense clouds.</l>
<l n="69">The very first the Iberian Sea, as we make our beginning,</l>
<l n="70">flows forth, which is also the beginning of Europe</l>
<l n="71">and of Libya; for it rolls between of the two.</l>
<l n="72">And the Pillars lie here and there, near the edges,</l>
<l n="73">the one Pillar looking at Europe, the other toward Libya.</l>
<l n="74">After this comes next the Galatian stream, where the land</l>
<l n="75">of Massalia stretches, with its curved harbour.</l>
<l n="76">Next after these, flows the sea of Liguria,</l>
<l n="77">there the sons of the Italoi dwell on the land,</l>
<l n="78">from Ausonian Zeus descended, always mighty rulers,</l>
<l n="79">beginning from the north as far as the White Rock,</l>
<l n="80">which is rooted on the Sicilian strait;</l>
<l n="81">Next the briny water is disgorged on Kyrnus.</l>
<l n="82">After this the Sardinian Sea roars within;</l>
<l n="83">And after it, the wave of the Tyrrhenian Sea howls</l>
<l n="84">towards the south; but then towards the rays of the sun</l>
<l n="85">the curved Sicilian current turns about; then below</l>
<l n="86">it pours forth even until the stormy Pachynos</l>
<l n="87">and the headland of Crete, which protrudes far into the sea,</l>
<l n="88">beside sacred Gortyna and mainland Phaestos,</l>
<l n="89">headlong, presenting the appearance of the head of a ram;</l>
<l n="90">and because of this they called it the Kriou Metopon.</l>
<l n="91">Indeed it also stretches towards the Iapygian Land.</l>
<l n="92">From there, stretches out the Adriatic swell, widening</l>
<l n="93">towards the north, and then creeps anew towards a westerly creek,</l>
<l n="94">which those dwelling nearby also named the Ionian Sea.</l>
<l n="95">It disgorges itself upon two lands: for one who enters it,</l>
<l n="96">on the right hand appears the land Illyria,</l>
<l n="97">and Dalmatia is above, land of warlike men;</l>
<l n="98">and to the left is opening the immense isthmus of the Ausonioi,</l>
<l n="99">far-reaching, surrounded by three seas,</l>
<l n="100">the Tyrrhenian, the Sicilian, and the brimming Adriatic:</l>
<l n="101">each one directs its track into a wind,</l>
<l n="102">the Tyrrhenian the west-wind, the Sicilian the south-wind, the Adriatic the east-wind.</l>
<l n="103">But beyond the Sicilian land the sea flows</l>
<l n="104">towards Libya raising crested waves, rolling around the southern Syrtis, </l>
<l n="105">the one which they also call the Greater;</l>
<l n="106">the other one, which has a powerless path, being farther in,</l>
<l n="107">receives a rise of the sea that comes from afar.</l>
<l n="108">So do the two gulfs roll as they twist and turn;</l>
<l n="109">and from the Sicilian mountains stretches the swell of Crete</l>
<l n="110">far to the east, as far as the Salmonian peak,</l>
<l n="111">which they say is the eastern headland of Crete.</l>
<l n="112">Next, two further seas tremble,</l>
<l n="113">driven by the blasts of the Ismarian north-wind,</l>
<l n="114">which blows straight, for they lie opposite.</l>
<l n="115">Sailors call the first the Pharian Sea,</l>
<l n="116">which stretches to the furthermost foreland of Casius,</l>
<l n="117">the Sidonian the other, where stretches into the nook of land</l>
<l n="118">as far as the city of Issus, passing by the country of the Cilici,</l>
<l n="119">the boundless sea of Issus, flowing northward,</l>
<l n="120">keeping pace not very far: for already near</l>
<l n="121">the dark turning point of the land of the Cilici it terminates;</l>
<l n="122">then it disgorges the pliant swell to the west-wind.</l>
<l n="123">Just as a grim-looking serpent turns, coiled and creeping,</l>
<l n="124">sluggish, and beneath it the entire headland of a mountain is weighed down,</l>
<l n="125">as it moves, so turns this gulf in the sea, </l>
<l n="126">full-flowing, here and there weighed down by flood-waters.</l>
<l n="127">Around its flood-waters the Pamphylii dwell,</l>
<l n="128">as far as it reaches until the Chelidoniae Islands;</l>
<l n="129">it has as its far boundary-mark in the west the headland of Patara.</l>
<l n="130">Consider now, turning from there again to the Bears,</l>
<l n="131">the wide current of the Aegean sea, where the wave</l>
<l n="132">roars as it breaks against the Sporades Islands:</l>
<l n="133">no other current raises waves equal to that one,</l>
<l n="134">boiling from the depths, no other path of the sea.</l>
<l n="135">It put forth its boundary until the extreme point of Tenedos,</l>
<l n="136">with Imbros on the other side, whence a narrow strait proceeds,</l>
<l n="137">sweeping northward within the entire Propontis.</l>
<l n="138">Beyond it stretch countless tribes of the Asian land,</l>
<l n="139">towards the south: for a broad isthmus of land starts afterwards.</l>
<l n="140">After this is the mouth of the Thracian Bosporos, which Io once </l>
<l n="141">swam at Hera's instigation, as a young heifer.</l>
<l n="142">That is indeed the narrowest ferry</l>
<l n="143">of all the others, which belong to the stormy sea,</l>
<l n="144">where the shameless Cyanea Rocks, the story goes, in the sea</l>
<l n="145">roam and clash with a loud noise against one another.</l>
<l n="146">From here opens up and spreads nearby the Pontus,</l>
<l n="147">being large and sprawling into the large nook to the east.</l>
<l n="148">Its ways, moreover, run forward obliquely,</l>
<l n="149">always looking towards the north and the east;</l>
<l n="150">and in the middle, here and there, rise two hilltops,</l>
<l n="151">the one on the far south, they call it Karambis,</l>
<l n="152">the other further north, above the European land,</l>
<l n="153">which the neighbouring people call the Kriou Metopon;</l>
<l n="154">these two meet face to face, although they are not</l>
<l n="155">near one another, but are as far apart as a trading vessel might travel in three days.</l>
<l n="156">From here you could also see that the Pontus is two seas,</l>
<l n="157">and in its curvature resembles a circular tied bow:</l>
<l n="158">now the shape of the bowstring would be the right-hand portion of the Pontus,</l>
<l n="159">drawn straight, but Karambis is alone midway,</l>
<l n="160">standing outside the line and looking to the north.</l>
<l n="161">The left-hand path hast he shape of horns, it is bent in a double</l>
<l n="162">curve, like the horns of a bow.</l>
<l n="163">And towards the north the waters of the lake Maeotis</l>
<l n="164">pour forth. Around this dwell the Scythoi,</l>
<l n="165">countless men, and they call it the mother of the Pontus:</l>
<l n="166">for from this flows the measureless water of the Pontus,</l>
<l n="167">straight through the Kimmerian Bosporus, on which many</l>
<l n="168">Kimmeri dwell under the cold foot of Tauros.</l>
<l n="169">Such then is the appearance of the dark-gleaming sea;</l>
<l n="170">and now I will tell you about the shape of every continent,</l>
<l n="171">so that without seeing it still you should have an intelligible view,</l>
<l n="172">and as a result of this you should be honoured and well regarded,</l>
<l n="173">as you relate particulars to someone uninformed.</l>
<l n="174">Well, then, Libya goes stretching into the south,</l>
<l n="175">into the south and east, similar in outline to a trapezium,</l>
<l n="176">beginning first from Gadeira, where the pointed extremity</l>
<l n="177">extends into a nook of Ocean;</l>
<l n="178">It put forth its wider boundary until the Arabian sea,</l>
<l n="179">where the land of the dark Aethiopii is,</l>
<l n="180">the other ones, near whom stretches the soil of the Erembi;</l>
<l n="181">men say, it is similar to a leopard-skin:</l>
<l n="182">for it lies indeed thirsty and without rain,</l>
<l n="183">here and there dotted with dark spots.</l>
<l n="184">So, then, below the outermost point there dwell</l>
<l n="185">near the pillars the peoples of the Maurusian land.</l>
<l n="186">After them extend the countless tribes of Nomads,</l>
<l n="187">where the Masaesylii and the country-dwelling Masylii</l>
<l n="188">go to pasture with their children through plain and forest,</l>
<l n="189">pursuing a lowly and wretched hunt for sustenance,</l>
<l n="190">for they did not learn the cut of the earth-dividing plough,</l>
<l n="191">nor is the delightful drawing of a wagon ever heard by them,</l>
<l n="192">nor is the lowing of cattle coming into the stable;</l>
<l n="193">but even so, just as wild beasts, they herd through the thickets,</l>
<l n="194">ignorant of corn and unaware of the harvest.</l>
<l n="195">After them Karchedon surrounds a very lovely harbor,</l>
<l n="196">Karchedon, belonging to the Libyi, but formerly to the Phoenices,</l>
<l n="197">Karchedon, which the story says was measured by an ox-hide.</l>
<l n="198">Next in order, the Syrtis rolls a strong-flowing course,</l>
<l n="199">the lesser; after this, towards the east, the other one flows,</l>
<l n="200">immense, weighed down with broader flood-waters;</l>
<l n="201">there, as the Tyrrhenian sea crests, </l>
<l n="202">at one time a flood-tide is stirred up, but at another time in turn</l>
<l n="203">the ebbing sea runs over the dry sands.</l>
<l n="204">In the middle of these two a city stands,</l>
<l n="205">which they call Neapolis; beyond it the land</l>
<l n="206">inhabit the Lotus Eaters, hospitable from birth:</l>
<l n="207">here the wily Odysseus once came in his wanderings.</l>
<l n="208">Then, in that region the deserted homes</l>
<l n="209">of the perished Nasamones men you could observe,</l>
<l n="210">for the Ausonian spear destroyed them, who paid no heed to Zeus.</l>
<l n="211">After them are the inland Asbystai</l>
<l n="212">and the precinct of the Libyan deity, under much sand,</l>
<l n="213">and Cyrene of the fine horses, seat of Amyclaean men;</l>
<l n="214">nearby are the Marmaridae, spreading toward Aegyptus,</l>
<l n="215">and the Gaetuli beyond them and the neighbouring Nigretes.</l>
<l n="216">Next after these are the Phaurusii, beyond whose the land</l>
<l n="217">inhabit the innumerable Garamantes; in the remote nooks</l>
<l n="218">of the continent feed the furthermost Aethiopii,</l>
<l n="219">by the Ocean itself, near the vales of farthest Cerne.</l>
<l n="220">Before them rise up the peaks of the smoky Blemyoi,</l>
<l n="221">whence descend the waters of the most-fertile Neilos,</l>
<l n="222">which indeed, creeping mightily from Libya toward the east,</l>
<l n="223">is called Siris by the Aethiopii; the inhabitants of Syene</l>
<l n="224">once it has turned, gave it the name Neilos.</l>
<l n="225">From there stretching to the north, this way and that,</l>
<l n="226">and rolling through seven mouths it falls into the sea,</l>
<l n="227">enriching with its waters the fruitful plain of Aegyptus.</l>
<l n="228">For no river is like the Neilos,</l>
<l n="229">not in depositing silt, nor in increasing the wealth of the earth;</l>
<l n="230">this river also divides Libya from the Asian land,</l>
<l n="231">to the west Libya, and to the east the Asian land.</l>
<l n="232">Around it dwells a race of the most illustrious men,</l>
<l n="233">who were the first to distinguish the ways of life,</l>
<l n="234">the first to make trial of the lovely plough</l>
<l n="235">and spread seed over the very straight furrow,</l>
<l n="236">and the first to measured the sky with lines,</l>
<l n="237">pondering in their minds the oblique course of the sun.</l>
<l n="238">I shall tell of them and of the limits of their land itself</l>
<l n="239">and of its appearance; for it has been allotted no small share of honour;</l>
<l n="240">and is it of no small size, but beyond others</l>
<l n="241">it abounds in pasture and goodly meadows and brings forth all splendid things.</l>
<l n="242">Its shape, then, is based on three sides,</l>
<l n="243">broad by the northern extremities, and being drawn out sharp to the dawn</l>
<l n="244">and as far as high-peaked Syene,</l>
<l n="245">fortified on both sides by all-sheltering mountains,</l>
<l n="246">through the middle of which descend the waters of the beautiful-flowing Neilos.</l>
<l n="247">And many and prosperous men occupy it,</l>
<l n="248">both as many as inhabit very-famous Thebes,</l>
<l n="249">Thebes pristine, hundred-gated, where sonorously</l>
<l n="250">Memnon greets his Dawn as she rises,</l>
<l n="251">and as many as occupy the midmost land of seven cities,</l>
<l n="252">and as many as there are on the moist shores of the sea,</l>
<l n="253">occupying the coast until the Lake Serbonis.</l>
<l n="254">To the west of this is the Macedonian city,</l>
<l n="255">where the house of great Zeus Sinopita is,</l>
<l n="256">adorned by precious gold. No other</l>
<l n="257">more divine temple you could see among men,</l>
<l n="258">nor another city as wealthy, where</l>
<l n="259">appear high watch-towers of Pallenian Eidothea.</l>
<l n="260">After this toward the east, near Mount Casius, </l>
<l n="261">the city named after Peleus is occupied by men</l>
<l n="262">above others skilled in seafaring. Those </l>
<l n="263">men are not reckoned among the Libyi: for </l>
<l n="264">they have obtained a city situated to the east of the seven-mounted Neilos;</l>
<l n="265">a great many others also inhabit this land:</l>
<l n="266">some by the Ocean, some in the centre of the continent,</l>
<l n="267">the others around the waters of the beloved Lake Triton,</l>
<l n="268">which in the middle of Libya embraces a broad sea.</l>
<l n="269">Such is the appearance and shape of Libya.</l>
<l n="270">If you wish an outline of Europe too, I will not hide it from you.</l>
<l n="271">Its configuration is the same as of Libya, but toward the north</l>
<l n="272">it is aligned and creeps back toward the east</l>
<l n="273">just as that of the southerly Libya moves towards its boundary:</l>
<l n="274">both alike have their furthest track at Asia,</l>
<l n="275">the one towards the north, the other to the south. And if you would make</l>
<l n="276">these the two of them one land, then altogether</l>
<l n="277">it would be a shape of a cone, equal on its two sides,</l>
<l n="278">pointed in the west, but broad in the east at the middle.</l>
<l n="279">Therefore, having seen such an outline of both</l>
<l n="280">continents, you would easily grasp the bounds of Europe.</l>
<l n="281">Well, then, at its outermost side dwell,</l>
<l n="282">near the Pillars, the people of the great-hearted Iberi,</l>
<l n="283">reaching across the length of the continent, where </l>
<l n="284">the cold stream of the northern Ocean flows, there the Bretanoi</l>
<l n="285">and the white tribes of the war-mad Germani dwell,</l>
<l n="286">running beside the mountains of the Hercynian forest.</l>
<l n="287">They say that that land resembles an ox-hide.</l>
<l n="288">And after Iberi are the Pyrenean mountain and the homes of the Celti,</l>
<l n="289">near the springs of the beautiful-flowing Eridanus,</l>
<l n="290">beside the flood-waters of which once at the desolate night</l>
<l n="291">the Heliades cried, lamenting Phaethon;</l>
<l n="292">there the children of the Celti, seated beneath the poplars,</l>
<l n="293">collect the tear-drops of gold-gleaming amber.</l>
<l n="294">Next after this are the abodes of the Tyrrhenian land:</l>
<l n="295">towards the east of this appears the beginning of the Alpes,</l>
<l n="296">through the middle of which rush down the waters of the Rhenus</l>
<l n="297">towards the furthermost stream of the Northern sea.</l>
<l n="298">Next after the Rhenus there arises the sacred Istros</l>
<l n="299">itself, reaching to the east as far as the Sea</l>
<l n="300">of Euxine, where it disgorges its entire froth of water,</l>
<l n="301">rolling around Peuce with its five-fold stream.</l>
<l n="302">Towards the north of Istros dwell very many scattered tribes,</l>
<l n="303">one next to the other, as far as the mouth of the lake Maeotis,</l>
<l n="304">Germani, and Samatae, and Getae, and also Bastarnae,</l>
<l n="305">and the endless land of the Daci and the valiant Alanoi,</l>
<l n="306">and the Tauri, who inhabit the steep Course of Achilles,</l>
<l n="307">both narrow and long, even as far as the mouth of the lake itself.</l>
<l n="308">Above these extends the tribe of the Agauoi rich in horses.</l>
<l n="309">There also the Melanchlaeni and men Hippemolgi,</l>
<l n="310">and the Neuri, and Hippopodes, and Geloni, also Agathyrsoi;</l>
<l n="311">where the far-stretching water of the river Borysthenes</l>
<l n="312">mixes with the Euxine before the Kriou Metopon,</l>
<l n="313">directly in a line opposite the Cyaneae.</l>
<l n="314">There also the waters of the Aldescus and of the Panticapes</l>
<l n="315">roar in their two separate paths in the Rhipaean mountains.</l>
<l n="316">At their flood-waters, near the Frozen sea,</l>
<l n="317">sweet-shining amber flourishes, just as a ray </l>
<l n="318">of the waxing moon; the radiant adamant</l>
<l n="319">you could see nearby, beside the cold Agathyrsoi.</l>
<l n="320">So many, then, are the peoples north of the Istros;</l>
<l n="321">and towards the south are the Gerrhae and the dark Norican towns,</l>
<l n="322">the Pannonii and the Moesii, farther north from the Thracoi,</l>
<l n="323">and the Thracoi themselves, who inhabit limitless land,</l>
<l n="324">some on the shores of the Propontic Sea,</l>
<l n="325">some over the strong-flowing Hellespont, and others above</l>
<l n="326">the deep wave of the loud-roaring Aegean Sea itself.</l>
<l n="327">There, on the heights of bee-feeding Pallene</l>
<l n="328">springs the beautiful asterios stone, which like a star</l>
<l n="329">gleams, and the lychnis, just like a flame of fire.</l>
<l n="330">So many, then, are the peoples that dwell around the Istros river;</l>
<l n="331">consider now the remaining path of Europe, which extends on three</l>
<l n="332">pedestals towards the dawn, that of the Iberi,</l>
<l n="333">that of the Panhellenes, and that of the Ausonioi themself.</l>
<l n="334">Well, then, the outermost is that of the illustrious Iberi,</l>
<l n="335">neighbor of the Ocean on the west; on it stands</l>
<l n="336">the headland Alybe, one of the Pillars; beneath that</l>
<l n="337">is graceful Tartessus, land of men flowing in riches,</l>
<l n="338">and the Kempsi, who dwell under the foot of Pyrene.</l>
<l n="339">In the middle of the other two extends the Ausonian headland,</l>
<l n="340">far-stretching; a mountain cuts it in two down the middle,</l>
<l n="341">straight, just as i fit had been aligned with a carpenter's ruler; nor would</l>
<l n="342">a skillful servant of clever Athene find fault with it;</l>
<l n="343">this they call the Apennion: in the north</l>
<l n="344">beginning from the Alpes it ends at the Sicilian Strait.</l>
<l n="345">There are many tribes around it, about all of them I will easily tell you</l>
<l n="346">beginning with the western side from the north:</l>
<l n="347">the Tyrrheni first, and after them the tribes of Pelasgi,</l>
<l n="348">who once, came from Kyllene to the western sea,</l>
<l n="349">where they settled alongside the Tyrrhenian men.</l>
<l n="350">After them is the warlike nation of illustrious Latini,</l>
<l n="351">who inhabit a delightsome land, through the middle of which</l>
<l n="352">the rolling Thymbris casts its pure stream into the sea</l>
<l n="353">the fair-flowing Thymbris, most kingly of all rivers,</l>
<l n="354">the Thymbris, which divides in two lovely Rome,</l>
<l n="355">honored Rome, the great home of my lords,</l>
<l n="356">mother of all cities, rich abode.</l>
<l n="357">After this is the fertil plain of the Campani, where </l>
<l n="358">is the house of chaste Parthenope, laden with the sheaves of grain,</l>
<l n="359">Parthenope, whom the sea welcomed in its bosom.</l>
<l n="360">Towards the south, quite far beyond the rock of the Sirens,</l>
<l n="361">appear the flood-waters of the Picentine Silarus;</l>
<l n="362">nearby are the Leucani and the men Brentioi,</l>
<l n="363">inhabiting as much land as far the White Rock.</l>
<l n="364">From there to the north appears the headland of Zephyr;</l>
<l n="365">below it are the Locri, all those who in years gone by,</l>
<l n="366">came to Ausonia, after coupling with their mistresses,</l>
<l n="367">whose race even now lives on the flood-waters of the Halex river.</l>
<l n="368">Next after these are the Metapontii; and near them</l>
<l n="369">is the lovely city of tower-girded Croton,</l>
<l n="370">situated at the flood-waters of the graceful Aisaros,</l>
<l n="371">where you could see the lofty temple of Lacinian Hera.</l>
<l n="372">There is also in that place, at the anger of mighty Zeus</l>
<l n="373">is wretched Sybaris, lamenting fallen inhabitants,</l>
<l n="374">who were overly mad for honors of Alpheios.</l>
<l n="375">The Samnites after them inhabit the middle land</l>
<l n="376">and the nimble tribes of the Marsi; Tarentum lies near the sea,</l>
<l n="377">which the strong Ares of the Amyclaeans once fortified.</l>
<l n="378">Next after these are the settlements of the Calabrian land,</l>
<l n="379">and the tribes of Iapyges extending as far as Hyrium</l>
<l n="380">by the sea, Hyrium, where the swell of the Adriatic sweeps</l>
<l n="381">into the neighboring sea of Aquileia, where stands</l>
<l n="382">the city of the Tegestraei, on the edges of the innermost sea.</l>
<l n="383">So many nations find sustenance on the Ausonian land.</l>
<l n="384">From there to the east the winding swell sweeps,</l>
<l n="385">wearing at the Liburnian shores, and around all</l>
<l n="386">the fortified land of the Hylleans, as much as lies on the isthmus,</l>
<l n="387">and the shores of the Boulimoi; driving onward its immense course</l>
<l n="388">it turns around the Illyrian land as far as the peak</l>
<l n="389">and the lofty mountains, which they call the Ceraunii.</l>
<l n="390">Moreover, in that region you could see a circular barrow,</l>
<l n="391">a barrow which rumour has it belongs to Harmonia and Cadmos:</l>
<l n="392">for in that place they were changed into the race of coiling serpents,</l>
<l n="393">when they came from Ismenus in flourishing old age.</l>
<l n="394">Here the gods brought about another miracle for them: for around that land</l>
<l n="395">on either side stand two rocks,</l>
<l n="396">which come together shaking, whenever any evil</l>
<l n="397">arising begins to roll upon the inhabitants.</l>
<l n="398">Towards the south, quite far beyond fertile Thrace</l>
<l n="399">and beyond the Orician land stands the beginning of Hellas,</l>
<l n="400">extruding far, girded by a two-fold sea,</l>
<l n="401">the Aegean and the Sicilian; each has been allotted a wind,</l>
<l n="402">the Sicilian Sea the west wind, they also call it Zephyr,</l>
<l n="403">the Aegean the east wind. Next follows the island of Pelops,</l>
<l n="404">shaped like the tapering leaf of a plane-tree.</l>
<l n="405">For the narrow Isthmus is constricted like a stem</l>
<l n="406">towards the north, and leans upon Hellas with a common track:</l>
<l n="407">the large land is similar to a leaf with many sinuosities,</l>
<l n="408">wreathed with coastal bays here and there.</l>
<l n="409">Towards its west are the abodes of the Triphylian land,</l>
<l n="410">where the loveliest of rivers, the Alpheios, makes its way,</l>
<l n="411">separating from the flood-waters of the Messenian Eurotas,</l>
<l n="412">both these rivers spout forth their streams from ground:</l>
<l n="413">but the one divides the country of the Elioi, the other that of the Amyclaeans.</l>
<l n="414">In the middle of the island inhabit a hollow country</l>
<l n="415">the Apidanian Arcadoi, beneath the peak of Erymanthos,</l>
<l n="416">where Melas, where Crathis, where the moist Iaon flows,</l>
<l n="417">where also the primeval Ladon enlarges with its waters.</l>
<l n="418">Nearby is the soil of the Argeioi and the land of the Laconii,</l>
<l n="419">the one looking to the east, the other to the south.</l>
<l n="420">Two seas roar around the shores of the Isthmus,</l>
<l n="421">the one flowing opposite Ephyra towards the darkness, the other towards the dawn,</l>
<l n="422">this they call the Saronic.</l>
<l n="423">Beside the Isthmus towards the east is the Attic land,</l>
<l n="424">through which flows the stream of the divine Ilissos,</l>
<l n="425">and whence Boreas once snatched Oreithyia.</l>
<l n="426">After this there is the plain of the Boeotoi and the Locrian soil,</l>
<l n="427">and Thessaly, and after these the cities of Macedonia.</l>
<l n="428">After this appear the ridges of snowy Haemus</l>
<l n="429">in Thrace; before it towards the blast of the west wind</l>
<l n="430">lies in a circle the immense land of Dodona.</l>
<l n="431">Beyond it to the south there is, under the peak of Aracynthus,</l>
<l n="432">the great plain of Aetolian men; through the middle of it</l>
<l n="433">sweeps conducting its course the silver-eddying Achelous,</l>
<l n="434">rolling to the sea of Trinacria through the middle</l>
<l n="435">of islands, which they call the Echinades, and marching to which</l>
<l n="436">are spread here and there the cities of the Kephalleni.</l>
<l n="437">After this is the soil of Phocis, towards the east and the dawn,</l>
<l n="438">flowing northwards to the mouth of Thermopylae,</l>
<l n="439">under the fold of snow-clad Parnassos: through the middle of it</l>
<l n="440">the great stream of Cephisos babbles descending.</l>
<l n="441">Beside this is the fragrant plain of Pytho, where the coil</l>
<l n="442">of the serpent Delphyne bent around the tripod of the god,</l>
<l n="443">the coil bristling with countless scales,</l>
<l n="444">in the great temple, where often Apollo himself</l>
<l n="445">staying unlooses the cord of his golden quiver,</l>
<l n="446">when he has just come from Miletus or from Klaros.</l>
<l n="447">So, then, may he be gracious; and you, Muse of Zeus, tell me</l>
<l n="448">the sacred path of all the islands that in the sea</l>
<l n="449">appear to men, facing here and there.</l>
<l n="450">Well, then, in the middle under the western Pillars</l>
<l n="451">farthest Gadeira appears to men,</l>
<l n="452">on a seagirt island at the boundaries of Ocean.</l>
<l n="453">There dwells a race of Phoenician men,</l>
<l n="454">who worship the offspring of great Zeus, Heracles;</l>
<l n="455">and this island, which in the time of former people</l>
<l n="456">was called Cotinussa, the inhabitants named Gadeira.</l>
<l n="457">The Gymnesiae Islands are next; nearby is Busos,</l>
<l n="458">and broadest Sardinia and Kyrnos delightsome in the sea,</l>
<l n="459">which the people who live there call Corsis:</l>
<l n="460">there is no island so thickly grown with forest as that one.</l>
<l n="461">After this there are the islands of Aeolus, running round in the sea,</l>
<l n="462">Aeolus, son of Hippotas, hospitable king,</l>
<l n="463">Aeolus, who obtained gifts wondrous among men,</l>
<l n="464">sovereignty of the winds both raging and standing still.</l>
<l n="465">There are seven of them, named among people the Floating isles,</l>
<l n="466">because in their midst they have a revolving passage that may be sailed around.</l>
<l n="467">After these Trinacria, beyond the territory of the Ausonioi,</l>
<l n="468">extends, standing on three sides:</l>
<l n="469">its headlands are Pachynos, Peloris, and Lilybe.</l>
<l n="470">So, then, Lilybe rises up into the blast of the west wind,</l>
<l n="471">and Pachynus towards the east, but towards the Bears</l>
<l n="472">windy Peloris, looking at Ausonia.</l>
<l n="473">Towards the north from Peloris the way is deadly for sailors,</l>
<l n="474">narrow, and crooked, and unruly, where the sea</l>
<l n="475">sweeping roars about large rocks,</l>
<l n="476">pierced by the many-barbed Aonian iron.</l>
<l n="477">Towards the south is the Libyan path and the beginning of the Syrtis,</l>
<l n="478">the one; the other you would see as you made your way further,</l>
<l n="479">the western one. In front of it are two islets,</l>
<l n="480">Meninx and Cercinna, containing the Libyan anchorage.</l>
<l n="481">But whenever you sail the left-hand path of the Adriatic sea</l>
<l n="482">in your ship, to the Iapygian land,</l>
<l n="483">you find at once the island of powerful Diomedes,</l>
<l n="484">where the hero came, when Aphrodite was provoked,</l>
<l n="485">when he was journeying to the people of very distant Iberi,</l>
<l n="486">because of the designs of his wife, ill-minded Aegialeia.</l>
<l n="487">Next after this path, towards the rays of the sun,</l>
<l n="488">appears the immense course of the islands of Apsyrtos,</l>
<l n="489">which once the sons of the Colchians invaded, when they toiled</l>
<l n="490">as they sought the tracks of the errant daughter of Aietes.</l>
<l n="491">Next after these are rooted the Liburni.</l>
<l n="492">Towards the south, after the Ceraunian forests, to a passing ship</l>
<l n="493">there would appear from afar the islands of the Ampracians,</l>
<l n="494">and fruitful Cercyra, beloved land of Alcinous.</l>
<l n="495">After this is fixed the seat of Nerician Ithaca</l>
<l n="496">and of the other islands, as many as, creeping from Chalcis,</l>
<l n="497">the Achelous rolls with its silver eddies.</l>
<l n="498">Then, many islands are seen to the north of Amnisos,</l>
<l n="499">Aigila, and Cythera, and rugged Calauria;</l>
<l n="500">Carpathus is on the other side. Towards the darkness, near it,</l>
<l n="501">is honored Crete, nurse of great Zeus,</l>
<l n="502">large, and fruitful, and abounding in pasture, above which is Ida,</l>
<l n="503">Ida, flourishing with trees of beautiful foliage;</l>
<l n="504">and, mind you, its size is immense. Opposite the coast</l>
<l n="505">of Aegyptus is Rhodes, land of Ialysian men.</l>
<l n="506">After it, eastwards, are the Chelidoniae,</l>
<l n="507">three islands from inside the great promontory of Patara.</l>
<l n="508">Cyprus then is washed to the sunrise, within the Pamphylian gulf,</l>
<l n="509">the lovely city of Dionean Aphrodite.</l>
<l n="510">Near Phoenicia Arados is in the great gulf.</l>
<l n="511">Then before the peak Sounion, above the Abantes,</l>
<l n="512">appear Salamis and the city of Aegina.  </l>
<l n="513">Wondrous is the deep path of the Aegean,</l>
<l n="514">having within on either side a row of endless islands,</l>
<l n="515">as far as the narrow waters of Helle, daughter of Athamas,</l>
<l n="516">where Sestos and Abydos have established anchorage opposite one another.</l>
<l n="517">The islands of Europe lie beneath the wave of the left hand,</l>
<l n="518">if moving to Helle, those of Asia lie along the right,</l>
<l n="519">reaching lenghtways to the Arctic north.</l>
<l n="520">So Abantian Macris belongs to Europe,</l>
<l n="521">and windy Scyros, and lofty Peparethos;</l>
<l n="522">thence also Lemnos, the rocky land of Hephaestos,</l>
<l n="523">extends, and primeval Thasos, Demeter's shore,</l>
<l n="524">Imbros and Thracian Samos, the city of the Corybantes.</l>
<l n="525">The islands of Asia, which have obtained the first lot, lying around</l>
<l n="526">encircle Delos, and their name is Cyclades:</l>
<l n="527">All of them conduct dances as offerings to Apollo,</l>
<l n="528">when the sweet spring newly arrives, when in the mountains</l>
<l n="529">far away from people conceives the clear-voiced nightingale.</l>
<l n="530">Next the Islands of Sporades shine all around,</l>
<l n="531">as when stars are seen through the cloudless air,</l>
<l n="532">when the rushing north wind dispels humid clouds.</l>
<l n="533">After these are the Ionian islands: there are Caunos,</l>
<l n="534">and lovely Samos, seat of Pelasgian Hera,</l>
<l n="535">and Chios under the foot of lofty Pelinnaeus.</l>
<l n="536">From there appear the mountains of the Aeolian islands,</l>
<l n="537">spacious Lesbos and lovely Tenedos.</l>
<l n="538">There too the gulf of Melas spouts forth to the Hellespont,</l>
<l n="539">discharging foam; as one goes far to the north,</l>
<l n="540">there extends here and there the wave of the Propontic Sea.</l>
<l n="541">There is above the left-hand path of the Euxine,</l>
<l n="542">facing the Borysthenes, a very famous island in the sea,</l>
<l n="543">of heroes: they call it by the name Leuca,</l>
<l n="544">because the serpents there are white;</l>
<l n="545">there rumor has it the souls of Achilles and of the other heroes</l>
<l n="546">roam about through the desolate glens:</l>
<l n="547">this is the gift from Zeus which attends the most noble</l>
<l n="548">in reward of their virtue: for virtue obtains delightsome honor.</l>
<l n="549">Now as you go straight through the Kimmerian Bosporus</l>
<l n="550">there is another immense island, which is fixed</l>
<l n="551">within the lake Maeotis on the right-hand side,</l>
<l n="552">on which are Phainagora and well-built Hermonassa,</l>
<l n="553">where dwell descendants of the Ionian land.</l>
<l n="554">These are the islands in the sea famous among men;</l>
<l n="555">and the others are wreathed along Ocean's stream:</l>
<l n="556">whose notable positions I would tell,</l>
<l n="557">and at the foot of which wind each is located.</l>
<l n="558">So, then, there dwell around ox-feeding Erytheia,</l>
<l n="559">somewhere near the stream of Atlas, the god-fearing Aethiopii,</l>
<l n="560">blameless sons of the Macrobians, who once came there</l>
<l n="561">after the death of arrogant Geryon; but behind the Sacred</l>
<l n="562">Cape, which they say is the top of Europe,</l>
<l n="563">the islands of the Hesperides, the birthplace of tin,</l>
<l n="564">are inhabited by the rich children of the illustrious Iberi.</l>
<l n="565">Near the northern shores of the Ocean</l>
<l n="566">There are two others islands, the British Isles, opposite the Rhenus:</l>
<l n="567">for there it discharges its last eddy into the sea.</l>
<l n="568">The magnitude of these islands is immense and no other</l>
<l n="569">among all the islands is equal to the British Isles.</l>
<l n="570">Nearby there is another path of islets, where the women</l>
<l n="571">of the noble Amnitian men from the opposite shore</l>
<l n="572">incited perform according to custom the sacred rites for Bacchus,</l>
<l n="573">wreathed with clusters of dark-leaved ivy</l>
<l n="574">by night; and the clear sound of tumult rises.</l>
<l n="575">Not so on the banks of the Thracian Apsinthos</l>
<l n="576">do the Bistonians call upon loud-shouting Eiraphiotes,</l>
<l n="577">not so with their children, along the dark-eddying Ganges,</l>
<l n="578">do the Indoi conduct their revelry for loud-thundering Dionysus,</l>
<l n="579">as throughout that region the women cry out "euoe".</l>
<l n="580">If you would cut further the long way of Ocean</l>
<l n="581">you would reach with the well-made ship the island Thule:</l>
<l n="582">there, when the sun has progressed to the pole of the Bears,</l>
<l n="583">the ever-shining fire streams out days and nights alike;</l>
<l n="584">for then it revolves in a rather oblique orbit,</l>
<l n="585">its rays coming at a direct descent,</l>
<l n="586">until it progresses along its southern way again toward the swarthy people;</l>
<l n="587">but whenever you cut the deep path of the Scythian Ocean</l>
<l n="588">with the ship, and you turn further toward the eastern sea,</l>
<l n="589">the path leads you to the island Chryseia, where even </l>
<l n="590">the rising of the clear sun itself appears.</l>
<l n="591">If from there you would turn along of the southern hilltop,</l>
<l n="592">quickly you would come upon the island of the great Colias,</l>
<l n="593">Taprobane, mother of the Asian-born elephants,</l>
<l n="594">above which, lifted up in heavenly orbit,</l>
<l n="595">the blazing Cancer turns in a circle in the aether;</l>
<l n="596">this island is very broad in magnitude; and all around</l>
<l n="597">sea-monsters inhabit the littoral waters, beasts of the Erythraean Sea,</l>
<l n="598">like lofty mountains; above the tops</l>
<l n="599">of their backs runs a very tall trace of spines.</l>
<l n="600">May the children of your enemies, as they turn about the sea,</l>
<l n="601">meet with these in wanderings; for there is no escape</l>
<l n="602">inside their wretched jaws, since it is a great yawning chasm;</l>
<l n="603">often they even gulp down a ship along with ship's men themselves</l>
<l n="604">those monsters; for a deity has placed for those who are wicked </l>
<l n="605">in the sea and on the land countless evils.</l>
<l n="606">There is further on, outside the Carmanian headland,</l>
<l n="607">Ogyris, where is the barrow of King Erythraios;</l>
<l n="608">from it you would reach the mouth of the Persian swell,</l>
<l n="609">if you set out northwards, and you would arrive at Icarus,</l>
<l n="610">maritime Icarus, where the Tauropolian goddess's</l>
<l n="611">altars, being full of sacrificial steam, have bitter smoke.</l>
<l n="612">So many islands meets the Ocean's current,</l>
<l n="613">the larger ones; and the others are immense,</l>
<l n="614">some in the flood-waters of the Libyan sea,</l>
<l n="615">some Asian, and some again around the region of Europe.</l>
<l n="616">The other islands elsewhere are countless, some being inhabited by men</l>
<l n="617">and affording lovely anchorage for ships,</l>
<l n="618">some having high cliffs and not being suitable for sailors,</l>
<l n="619">the names of all of these it would not be easy for me to relate.</l>
<l n="620">Now, the shape of Asia corresponds to the configuration of both other</l>
<l n="621">continents, from the other side resembling the outline of a cone,</l>
<l n="622">drawn gradually to the farthest nooks of the entire east,</l>
<l n="623">where too the pillars of Theban-born Dionysus</l>
<l n="624">stand, beside the current of the outermost Ocean,</l>
<l n="625">in the most distant mountains of the Indoi, and where</l>
<l n="626">the white water of the Ganges rolls to the Nysaean plain.</l>
<l n="627">But the size of the Asian land is not so great</l>
<l n="628">Nor is its outline entirely alike; for in those</l>
<l n="629">continents one sea governs the stream,</l>
<l n="630">but in Asia the great Ocean: for rolling three</l>
<l n="631">billowy gulfs, it disgorges them, casting them inland,</l>
<l n="632">the Persian, and the Arabian, and the deep-eddying Hyrcanian,</l>
<l n="633">two southerly, and one looking to the north,</l>
<l n="634">looking to the north and to the west, neighbor of the Pontus</l>
<l n="635">Euxine, where innumerable people dwell all around.</l>
<l n="636">A boundary between the two marks an immense isthmus of land,</l>
<l n="637">stretching hither and thither with long plains.</l>
<l n="638">The middle of all Asia a mountain-range encompasses,</l>
<l n="639">beginning at the Pamphylian land, as far as even the Indoi,</l>
<l n="640">sometimes oblique and curved, sometimes again</l>
<l n="641">completely straight in its tracks; they call it Tauros,</l>
<l n="642">because it looks like a bull and proceeds straight horned,</l>
<l n="643">split here and there into outstretched mountains.</l>
<l n="644">From there countless rivers flow with a loud noise,</l>
<l n="645">some towards the north, some to the south, some towards the blast</l>
<l n="646">of the east and west winds; who could tell the names of them all?</l>
<l n="647">It has not been allotted one name, but in each</l>
<l n="648">vale it has a different name; but these names would be of concern</l>
<l n="649">to those men who have established their home in the bordering land.</l>
<l n="650">Now, then, I will go through all the tribes, as many distinctly</l>
<l n="651">dwell there: may the Muses lead the most straight track.</l>
<l n="652">So then, near the Palus Maeotis dwell</l>
<l n="653">the Maeotians themselves and the tribes of Sauromatae,</l>
<l n="654">the brave race of warlike Ares; for they were born</l>
<l n="655">from that powerful love of the Amazonides,</l>
<l n="656">in which they once mingled with the Sauromatae men,</l>
<l n="657">after they wandered from their homeland far from Thermodon.</l>
<l n="658">Therefore, great-hearted children were born too,</l>
<l n="659">who inhabit a limitless forest, through the middle of which</l>
<l n="660">the Tanais sweeps and falls into the middle of Maeotis,</l>
<l n="661">which also divides Europe from the Asian land,</l>
<l n="662">Europe being to the side of sunset and the Asian land to the side of the sunrise.</l>
<l n="663">So its springs in the Caucasus Mountains</l>
<l n="664">roar afar; broad, rushing here and there,</l>
<l n="665">it runs over the Scythian plains.</l>
<l n="666">There, when the north wind swells beyond measure,</l>
<l n="667">you would see the frost congealed from the icy chill.</l>
<l n="668">Wretched are those who have their homes around that land;</l>
<l n="669">they always have cold snow and stormy chill;</l>
<l n="670">indeed, when the greatest cold comes out of the winds</l>
<l n="671">you could see before your eyes horses dying</l>
<l n="672">or even mules or the race of sheep who dwell in the fields;</l>
<l n="673">Moreover, not even men themselves would remain</l>
<l n="674">unharmed, if they should endure those blasts;</l>
<l n="675">but they roam, after yoking their wagons,</l>
<l n="676">into another place, leaving their land</l>
<l n="677">to the wintry gales which rage with evil whirlwinds,</l>
<l n="678">agitating both the mainland and the pine-covered mountains.</l>
<l n="679">So many dwell around the Tanais river.</l>
<l n="680">Beside the Sauromatae one after another are</l>
<l n="681">the Sindi, and the Kimmeri, and near the Euxine</l>
<l n="682">the Kerketai, and the Toretai and the valiant Achaeoi,</l>
<l n="683">whom the blasts of the south and the west wind</l>
<l n="684">once separated from Xanthos and Idaean Simoeis,</l>
<l n="685">as they followed their warlike king after battle.</l>
<l n="686">After these dwell, inhabiting a neighboring land,</l>
<l n="687">the Heniochi and Zygii, descendants of the Pelasgian land.</l>
<l n="688">Along the furthest nook of the Pontus, after the land of the Tyndaridae,</l>
<l n="689">the Colchians dwell, settlers from Aegyptus,</l>
<l n="690">near the Caucasus, which around the Hyrcanian Sea</l>
<l n="691">rises up in lofty mountains; there the Phasis also,</l>
<l n="692">winding along the back of the Circaean plain,</l>
<l n="693">disgorges swift foam to the swell of the Euxine,</l>
<l n="694 786">beginning first from the Armenian mountain.</l>
<l n="695">To the east and north of it lies an isthmus,</l>
<l n="696">an isthmus between the Caspian and of the Euxine seas.</l>
<l n="697">Upon it dwells the eastern tribe of Iberi,</l>
<l n="698">who once came from the Pyrene to the east,</l>
<l n="699">directing hateful battle against the Hyrcanian men,</l>
<l n="700">and the great tribe of Camaritae, who once welcomed Bacchus</l>
<l n="701">from the war of the Indoi and entertained him as a guest,</l>
<l n="702">and together with the Lenae established a sacred dance,</l>
<l n="703">placing loin-cloths and fawn-skins on their breasts,</l>
<l n="704">crying "Euoe, Bacche"; and the deity cherished in his heart</l>
<l n="705">the race of those people and the abodes of the land.</l>
<l n="706">After them, the Caspian Sea swells with waves.</l>
<l n="707">Easily I shall describe you also this sea,</l>
<l n="708">without having seen its far away paths, without having travelled in a ship;</l>
<l n="709">for my life is not on black ships,</l>
<l n="710">and my family is not in commerce, nor do I go to the Ganges,</l>
<l n="711">like others do, through the Erythraean sea,</l>
<l n="712">not caring for their lives, in order to win indescribable wealth,</l>
<l n="713">and I do not mix with the Hyrcanii, nor do I search</l>
<l n="714">for the Caucasian ridges of the Erythraean Arianoi;</l>
<l n="715">but the mind of the Muses conveys me, who are able to</l>
<l n="716">measure, without wandering about, much sea,</l>
<l n="717">as well as mountains and mainland and the course of the ethereal stars.</l>
<l n="718">So, then, the shape of the whole great Caspian Sea</l>
<l n="719">would be round, circular; you would not cross it</l>
<l n="720">in a ship up to the cycles of a third moon;</l>
<l n="721">for so great is its relentless path; flowing sharply to the Bears,</l>
<l n="722">it mixes with the flood-waters of Ocean;</l>
<l n="723">indeed it fosters many other wonders for men.</l>
<l n="724">It produces crystal and cloudy jasper,</l>
<l n="725">hostile to hobgoblins and other phantoms.</l>
<l n="726">I will tell you about all those tribes who dwell around it,</l>
<l n="727">beginning with the western side from the north.</l>
<l n="728">First are the Scythoi, as many as </l>
<l n="729">live at the mouth oft he Caspian see as far as the coast of the Cronion Sea.</l>
<l n="730">Next are the Thuni; beyond these are the Caspian men,</l>
<l n="731">and the warlike Albanoi after them, and beyond the rugged land</l>
<l n="732">dwell the Cadusioi; nearby are the Mardi,</l>
<l n="733">the Hyrcanii, and the Tapyri; after them winds its channel</l>
<l n="734">the Mardus, the drink of the Dercebii and the rich Bactroi;</l>
<l n="735">for between the two it falls into the Hyrcanian sea;</l>
<l n="736">so the Bactri inhabit a rather broad inland</l>
<l n="737">region beneath the ridges of Parnassos,</l>
<l n="738">and the Dercebii are on the other side by the Caspian waters.</l>
<l n="739">After them eastwards, beyond of the resounding Araxes,</l>
<l n="740">the Massagetae dwell, drawers of swift arrows,</l>
<l n="741">may neither I myself nor any companion approach</l>
<l n="742">these men: for they are much more hostile to strangers than others;</l>
<l n="743">for their food is not of delicious grain,</l>
<l n="744">nor even local wine; but rather by mixing</l>
<l n="745">white milk with the blood of horses they prepare their meal.</l>
<l n="746">After them towards the north are the Chorasmii, after them is the land</l>
<l n="747">of Sugdia, through the middle of which rolls the sacred Oxus,</l>
<l n="748">which leaves the Emodus mountain and falls into the Caspian.</l>
<l n="749">After it, beside the flood-waters of the Iaxartes, dwell</l>
<l n="750">the Sacae, bearing bows that no other archer</l>
<l n="751">could put to shame: for it is not customary for them to cast arrows in vain;</l>
<l n="752">there are the Tochari, and the Phruri, and barbarous tribes of the Seres,</l>
<l n="753">who reject cattle and fat sheep,</l>
<l n="754">and combing sheeny flowers of the desolate land,</l>
<l n="755">they produce skillfully wrought garments, costly,</l>
<l n="756">looking in color like the flowers of meadow herbs:</l>
<l n="757">no spider's work would rival them.</l>
<l n="758">And there are other populous Scythoi, who inhabit</l>
<l n="759">the farthest regions; beside them stretches a stormy land,</l>
<l n="760">left to the wintry winds and hail.</l>
<l n="761">So many are the peoples around the Caspian waves;</l>
<l n="762">and consider now as we turn from the Colchi and the Phasis to the side of the sunset,</l>
<l n="763">by the edge of the Euxine, in abundance tribes of the Pontus</l>
<l n="764">as far as the Thracian mouth, where is the Chalcian land.</l>
<l n="765">First are the Byzeres and nearby the tribes of Becheires,</l>
<l n="766">the Macrones, and the Philyres, and those who inhabit mossynes</l>
<l n="767">of wood; near them are the Tibarenoi rich in lambs;</l>
<l n="768">and after them the Chalybes inhabiting a rough and hard</l>
<l n="769">land, experts in the working of toilsome iron,</l>
<l n="770">who, standing at loud-thundering anvils,</l>
<l n="771">never cease from labour and wretched praise.</l>
<l n="772">After them the alluvial soil of the Assyrian land stretches,</l>
<l n="773">where to the Amazonides from the Armenian mountain</l>
<l n="774">sends forth its white water the furious Thermodon,</l>
<l n="775">who once received the wandered Sinope, daughter of Asopos,</l>
<l n="776">and settled her as she lamented in his own land,</l>
<l n="777">at the commands of Zeus; for he, desiring of sweet love,</l>
<l n="778">removed her from her fatherland because she was unwilling;</l>
<l n="779">men even inhabit a city named after her.</l>
<l n="780">Around the frozen banks of that river </l>
<l n="781">you could cut the pure stone of crystal, like ice </l>
<l n="782">of winter; you will also find watery jasper.</l>
<l n="783">Next the Iris casts a pure current into the sea.</l>
<l n="784">After this there roar the currents of the Halys river,</l>
<l n="785">coursing northwards near the headland of Karambis,</l>
<l n="694 786">beginning first from the Armenian mountain.</l>
<l n="787">After those currents the Paphlagonii dwell on the shores,</l>
<l n="788">and is the sacred plain of the Mariandyni: there they say</l>
<l n="789">the great brazen-voiced dog of Infernal Cronides,</l>
<l n="790">dragged up by the hands of great-hearted Heracles,</l>
<l n="791">vomited from his mouth terrible slobbery chyle,</l>
<l n="792">which the earth received and planted as a bane for men.</l>
<l n="793">Nearby the Bithynoi inhabit a fertile land,</l>
<l n="794">the Rhebas there sends forth a lovely stream,</l>
<l n="795">the Rhebas, which courses near the mouth of the Pontus,</l>
<l n="796">the Rhebas, whose water is the most beautiful that sweeps over the earth.</l>
<l n="797">So many men dwell around the Pontus;</l>
<l n="798">and let the tribes of Scythia be considered those as mentioned above.</l>
<l n="799">But now, then, I would proclaim the path of the Asian seaboard,</l>
<l n="800">which goes towards the south at the Hellespont,</l>
<l n="801">extending even to the southern current of the very expansive Aegean</l>
<l n="802">as far as Syria itself and lovely Arabia.</l>
<l n="803">First, the Chalcidees hold the land at the mouth,</l>
<l n="804">looking at the soil of Byzantium on the opposite coast;</l>
<l n="805">after them the Bebrykes and the mountains of the Mysian land,</l>
<l n="806">where Kios casts forth its beloved streams,</l>
<l n="807">at the flood-waters of which a nymph once snatched away Hylas,</l>
<l n="808">the ready servant of mighty Heracles.</l>
<l n="809">From there to Hellespont runs back the immense curve</l>
<l n="810">of Lesser Phrygia; the other one lies inland,</l>
<l n="811">is broader, beside the waters of the Sangarius;</l>
<l n="812">now then, the Greater Phrygia extends to the east,</l>
<l n="813">grazed by horses and fertile; whereas towards the west you would see</l>
<l n="814">the other Phrygia, which lies under the foot of divine Ida,</l>
<l n="815">and has wind-blown Ilion at its side,</l>
<l n="816">Ilion, splendid city of heroes born long ago,</l>
<l n="817">Ilion, which Poseidon and Apollo founded,</l>
<l n="818">Ilion, which Athene and Hera destroyed,</l>
<l n="819">beside the broad-flowing Xanthos and Idaean Simoeis.</l>
<l n="820">After this extend the abodes of the Aeolian land,</l>
<l n="821">by the edge of the Aegean, beyond the great Hellespont.</l>
<l n="822">After this dwell the children of the illustrious Ionians,</l>
<l n="823">near the sea, in the land through the middle of which</l>
<l n="824">the Maeander descends into the sea with fertile eddies,</l>
<l n="825">between Miletus and spacious Priene.</l>
<l n="826">Farther north of these two you would see</l>
<l n="827">maritime Ephesus, the great city of the arrow-pouring goddess,</l>
<l n="828">where the Amazonides once build a temple for the goddess</l>
<l n="829">on the trunk of an elm-tree, an extraordinary wonder to men.</l>
<l n="830">After them Maeonia extends into the east,</l>
<l n="831">under windy Tmolos, whence Pactolus on its way</l>
<l n="832">brings gold in its eddies and babbles;</l>
<l n="833">sitting on its banks in the spring season</l>
<l n="834">you could hear the clear voices of swans, which along the water</l>
<l n="835">here and there graze on the prospering grass;</l>
<l n="836">for many meadows flourish in Asia,</l>
<l n="837">especially along the plain of the Maeander, where the splendid water</l>
<l n="838">of the gently-plashing Kaystros flows.</l>
<l n="839">You certainly would not find fault with the women either, who around that</l>
<l n="840">divine seat, wearing a cord of gold around their waists,</l>
<l n="841">dance, turning in a wondrous circle,</l>
<l n="842">when they perform the chorus of Dionysus;</l>
<l n="843">with them the maidens skip, like young fawns;</l>
<l n="844">and round about them rustle the sounding winds</l>
<l n="845">stir the charming tunics on their breasts.</l>
<l n="846">But this is the concern of the Lydian people;</l>
<l n="847">by the sea the Lycii inhabit a land</l>
<l n="848">beside the flood-waters of the Xanthos, a fair-flowing river;</l>
<l n="849">there appear the mountains of the high-cliffed Tauros,</l>
<l n="850">even as far as the Pamphylii; they call it Cragus.</l>
<l n="851">There you could observe a city on the sea,</l>
<l n="852">Aspendos, beside the current of the river Eurymedon,</l>
<l n="853">where they appease the daughther of Dione with the slaughter of swine.</l>
<l n="854">Next, there are other Pamphylian cities,</l>
<l n="855">Corycus, and Perge, and wind-blown Phaselis.</l>
<l n="856">Towards the east of these inhabit an inland region</l>
<l n="857">The Lykaones with their crooced bows, experts in war.</l>
<l n="858">After them is the fertile plain of the Pisidi, where are the cities</l>
<l n="859">Telmessos, and Lyrbe, and the one which build the people</l>
<l n="860">of the Amyclaeans once in a former time, Selge, of great fame in the land.</l>
<l n="861">From there to the sunrise a curved sea cuts</l>
<l n="862">a winding path, reaching far inland,</l>
<l n="863">a neighbor of the stormy Euxine Sea.</l>
<l n="864">That gulf draws around itself the tribes of Cilici,</l>
<l n="865">a long way to the east; they call it the Strait of Asia.</l>
<l n="866">And with it mixes the water of a number of rivers</l>
<l n="867">coming from afar, of the Pyramos and the Pinaros,</l>
<l n="868">and the winding Cydnus, which goes through the middle of Tarsos,</l>
<l n="869">well-built Tarsos, where once the horse Pegasus,</l>
<l n="870">lost a hoof, left behind a name for the place, when from the horse</l>
<l n="871">fell the hero Bellerophon on his way into the realm of Zeus.</l>
<l n="872">There also is the plain of Aleos, on the flat of which,</l>
<l n="873">far from humankind, he rested.</l>
<l n="874">Next are the many cities of the Cilici,</l>
<l n="875">Lyrnessus, and Mallus, and Anchialeia, and Soli,</l>
<l n="876">some inland, others near the sea itself.</l>
<l n="877">After these is the seat of Commagene and the cities of Syria,</l>
<l n="878">stretching far along the curved shore: for a channel</l>
<l n="879">of the grey sea turns around to the sunset, as far as the peak</l>
<l n="880">of a mountain near the sea, the high-cliffed Casius.</l>
<l n="881">Easily could I tell you about the remaining path</l>
<l n="882">of the lands of Asia: keep these words in your heart,</l>
<l n="883">nor let the favor of works achieved by toils be borne away by the winds.</l>
<l n="884">For if you should perceive this path clearly,</l>
<l n="885">then you would quickly declaim knowledgeably to others</l>
<l n="886">of rivers and of the position of cities and of each land.</l>
<l n="887">Now let there be a figure of four sides,</l>
<l n="888">extending into the east in long plains.</l>
<l n="889">You know, since you heard me say so at the beginning,</l>
<l n="890">that a mountain cuts all of Asia in two as far as Indoi.</l>
<l n="891">That would form the more northerly of the sides,</l>
<l n="892">and the Neilos would be the western side; the eastern side</l>
<l n="893">would be the Indian Ocean; and the southern the waves of the Erythraean Sea.</l>
<l n="894">Consider how I will now by land into the sunrise,</l>
<l n="895">beginning from Syria, where I left off; and no man</l>
<l n="896">could accuse me of giving a false account.</l>
<l n="897">Well, then, Syria goes beyond the nearby sea</l>
<l n="898">into the south and east, with a land that has many cities,</l>
<l n="899">which they call by the name "Hollow", because it is in the middle</l>
<l n="900">of mountain-peaks which render it low down,</l>
<l n="901">of the western Casius and of the eastern Libanus.</l>
<l n="902">And many prosperous men inhabit this land,</l>
<l n="903">not dwelling together with the same name, but separately,</l>
<l n="904">some inland, who are called Syrioi,</l>
<l n="905">others being near the sea, Phoenices by name,</l>
<l n="906">of the race of men, who were Erythraei,</l>
<l n="907">who first made an attempt on the sea with ships,</l>
<l n="908">and first turned their minds to sea-tossed commerce</l>
<l n="909">and observed the profound path of the heavenly stars,</l>
<l n="910">they inhabit Iope, and Gaza, and Elais,</l>
<l n="911">and primeval Tyre and the lovely land of Berytus,</l>
<l n="912">and maritime Byblos and wind-blown Sidon,</l>
<l n="913">situated beside the waters of the graceful Bostrenos,</l>
<l n="914">and fertile Tripolis, and Orthosis, and Marathos,</l>
<l n="915">and Laodice, which lies on the shores of the sea,</l>
<l n="916">and the Posideian tillage and sacred vales of Daphne,</l>
<l n="917">where is Antiocheia named after Antiochus,</l>
<l n="918">but in the midst of these is the city of Apameia;</l>
<l n="919">towards the east of it the watery Orontes sweeps down,</l>
<l n="920">unspeakably great, drawing a boundary through the middle of the land of Antiochus.</l>
<l n="921">The whole land is fertile and abounds in pasturage,</l>
<l n="922">so as to pasture flocks and to foster fruit on trees.</l>
<l n="923">Beyond it you would see, if you should travel southwards,</l>
<l n="924">the inmost path of the Arabian Gulf, which between</l>
<l n="925">Syria and lovely Arabia winds,</l>
<l n="926">turned a bit to the east as far as Elani.</l>
<l n="927">From there bends the land of the very prosperous Araboi,</l>
<l n="928">reaching far, girded by a two-fold sea,</l>
<l n="929">the Persian and the Arabian; each sea has been allotted a wind,</l>
<l n="930">the Arabian the westerly, the Persian the paths of the eastern wind.</l>
<l n="931">Now the southern coastline, turning eastwards,</l>
<l n="932">is washed by the Erythraean waves of the Ocean.</l>
<l n="933">And I will tell you about its positions: for especially</l>
<l n="934">wealthy and splendid people beyond all others inhabit it.</l>
<l n="935">That land, mind you, has been allotted an eminent wonder:</l>
<l n="936">it always smells pleasantly due to burnt perfumes,</l>
<l n="937">either of incense, or myrrh, or sweet-smelling reed,</l>
<l n="938">or even divinely ripe frankincense,</l>
<l n="939">or cassia; for indeed it was in that land</l>
<l n="940">that Zeus himself released Dionysus from his well-stitched thigh:</l>
<l n="941">and at his birth, there arose all sorts of fragrances.</l>
<l n="942">The flocks too then became weighed down with shaggy fleeces</l>
<l n="943">in the pasture, and lakes spontaneously flowed with waters;</l>
<l n="944">and birds from various uninhabited islands</l>
<l n="945">came bearing foliage of fresh cinnamon.</l>
<l n="946">And then Dionysus stretched fawn-skins over his shoulders</l>
<l n="947">and wreathed his beautiful hair with lovely ivy</l>
<l n="948">and, tipsy with wine, he brandished plaited thyrsi,</l>
<l n="949">and smiled as he showered the men with great wealth.</l>
<l n="950">For this reason even today the fields are thick with the foliage of frankincense,</l>
<l n="951">the mountains with gold, and the rivers, moreover, with perfumes;</l>
<l n="952">the inhabitants themselves constitute a very wealthy populace,</l>
<l n="953">exulting in soft golden robes;</l>
<l n="954">so, then, first beyond the slope of Libanus</l>
<l n="955">dwell the opulent people called Nabataioi;</l>
<l n="956">nearby are the Chalbasioi, and the Agreei, beyond whom the land</l>
<l n="957">of Chatramis is situated opposite the Persian land.</l>
<l n="958">Moreover, along the side of the Erythraean Sea dwell</l>
<l n="959">the Minnaei, and Sabae, and the neighboring Kletabeni.</l>
<l n="960">So many immense tribes inhabit Arabia,</l>
<l n="961">and, mind you, there are very many others; for it is especially large.</l>
<l n="962">Towards the opposite shore, under the blast of the west wind,</l>
<l n="963">appears the wretched ground of the mountain-dwelling Erembi,</l>
<l n="964">who live their life in hollowed-out rocks,</l>
<l n="965">naked and lacking possessions; then, on bodies</l>
<l n="966">burned by the heat the parched skin grows black;</l>
<l n="967">thus, just like wild animals, they roam and suffer hardships,</l>
<l n="968">not as the stock of delicately living Araboi; for in the matter of wealth</l>
<l n="969">the deity did not provide an equal share for all men.</l>
<l n="970">Now beyond Libanus, towards the rays of the sun,</l>
<l n="971">the extensive land of the other Syria lengthens out,</l>
<l n="972">reaching even as far as sea-washed Sinope:</l>
<l n="973">in the middle of this abundant land</l>
<l n="974">the Cappadocai dwell, experts in horsemanship,</l>
<l n="975">and the Assyrioi near the sea beside the mouth of the Thermodon.</l>
<l n="976">Towards the east of Syria, out from the rugged mountains,</l>
<l n="977">appears the current of the immeasurable river Euphrates,</l>
<l n="978">which first runs from the Armenian mountain</l>
<l n="979">long to the south, and back, winding in curves,</l>
<l n="980">facing the sun as it passes through the middle of Babylon,</l>
<l n="981">it disgorges swift foam into the swell of the Persian Sea,</l>
<l n="982">passing near Teredon with its furthermost flood-waters.</l>
<l n="983">After this, to the sunrise, the swiftest of all rivers,</l>
<l n="984">the fair-flowing Tigris, bears its current driving a steady course,</l>
<l n="985">being as far away as a strong and swift man would accomplish,</l>
<l n="986">if he travelled for seven days.</l>
<l n="987">There is in the middle a certain lake encircled by its waters,</l>
<l n="988">named Thonitis, into the corners of which flows the Tigris,</l>
<l n="989">sinking far below; and then emerging back again,</l>
<l n="990">it casts a swifter current downwards; you would not</l>
<l n="991">see among all the rivers another more rapid one.</l>
<l n="992">As much land as between the Euphrates and the Tigris,</l>
<l n="993">the neighboring peoples call it "Mesopotamia".</l>
<l n="994">No herdsman finds fault with the pastures of that region,</l>
<l n="995">nor anyone, who honors the horn-hoofed Pan with a syrinx,</l>
<l n="996">follows after flocks who dwell in the fields; nor man who</l>
<l n="997">tends plants make light of the comprehensive variety of fruits,</l>
<l n="998">such is the soil of that region, in fostering</l>
<l n="999">grass, pastures rich in flowers, and a stock of men</l>
<l n="1000">that is most fair and similar to the immortals.</l>
<l n="1001">Towards the north of it a fertile land</l>
<l n="1002">inhabit the Armenian men and the close-fighting Matieni,</l>
<l n="1003">who live in the mountains, along the river Euphrates,</l>
<l n="1004">abundant, and wealthy, and well knowing Ares.</l>
<l n="1005">Towards the south is the sacred city of Babylon, the whole of which</l>
<l n="1006">Semiramis crowned with unbreakable walls;</l>
<l n="1007">moreover, on the acropolis she set up a great temple to Belus,</l>
<l n="1008">and adorned it with gold and ivory and silver.</l>
<l n="1009">And the surrounding plain of Babylon is immense, where many</l>
<l n="1010">overhanging date-palms with leafy crown grow.</l>
<l n="1011">And yes, it bears something else more graceful than gold,</l>
<l n="1012">the sea-green stone of clear beryl, which around that land</l>
<l n="1013">is formed within serpentine stone in the jutting rocks.</l>
<l n="1014">Moreover, beyond Babylon, towards the blast of the north wind</l>
<l n="1015">the Kissoi, and Messabatae, and Chalonitae dwell;</l>
<l n="1016">but whenever you should travel along the front of the Armenian mountains,</l>
<l n="1017">to the sunrise, then you will find the valleys of the Medes.</l>
<l n="1018">Towards the north of them, a luxuriant land</l>
<l n="1019">have the Geli, and Mardi, and men Atropatenoi.</l>
<l n="1020">Towards the south dwell the tribes of the illustrious Medes,</l>
<l n="1021">descendants of that very glorious stock of</l>
<l n="1022">Aietes' daughter, blameless heroine.</l>
<l n="1023">For when, beside the current of the Actaean Ilissos,</l>
<l n="1024">she prepared the baneful drugs for the son of Pandionid,</l>
<l n="1025">she left that land out of shame,</l>
<l n="1026">wandering among humankind, came into the abundant land that shares her name,</l>
<l n="1027">not far from Colchi; to come to the land of the Colchians</l>
<l n="1028">it was not for her; for she feared the anger of her father.</l>
<l n="1029">For this reason yet now men expert in many drugs</l>
<l n="1030">inhabit that immense land, some on</l>
<l n="1031">the rocks themselves, which produce dark narcissite,</l>
<l n="1032">some pressed in the overgrown meadows,</l>
<l n="1033">pasturing beautiful flocks, that are weighed down by their fleeces,</l>
<l n="1034">many of this people reach into the east as far as the Caspian</l>
<l n="1035">Gates, which lie under hollow rocks,</l>
<l n="1036">keys to the Asian land, where the road</l>
<l n="1037">extends for those going both to the north and to the south,</l>
<l n="1038">one to the Hyrcanii, another to the mountains of the Persian land.</l>
<l n="1039">So, then, under the foot of the Caspian Gates</l>
<l n="1040">dwell the warlike Parthoi, who have curved bows,</l>
<l n="1041">experts in all kinds of war; for they do not</l>
<l n="1042">trace the furrow with the plough, cleaving the fields,</l>
<l n="1043">nor do they in ships cut the sea with oars,</l>
<l n="1044">nor do they feed the race of cattle in pastures; but from birth,</l>
<l n="1045">even as infants, they concern themselves with bows and horses,</l>
<l n="1046">and always over this echoing land  there is the noise</l>
<l n="1047">of darts or arrows; and everywhere is the running of storm-footed horses</l>
<l n="1048">as they rush along; for it is not the way of things for them to partake of supper</l>
<l n="1049">until they besprinkle their heads with sweat by the toils of war;</l>
<l n="1050">they feed themselves with the quarry of a livelihood won by the spear;</l>
<l n="1051">but nevertheless, although they are irresistible in battle,</l>
<l n="1052">the spear of the Ausonian king has tamed them.</l>
<l n="1053">And if sweet desire to know the Persoi takes you,</l>
<l n="1054">fluently I would speak to you about their stock</l>
<l n="1055">and the paths of their ever-flowing rivers and the roads of their mountains.</l>
<l n="1056">For they alone have the most kingly nation of Asia,</l>
<l n="1057">and they alone placed boundless wealth in their homes,</l>
<l n="1058">when they sacked Maeonia and Sardis.</l>
<l n="1059">Golden is the armor on the frames of those people,</l>
<l n="1060">and golden are the bits in the mouths of their horses,</l>
<l n="1061">and with gold they adorn their sandals around their feet;</l>
<l n="1062">for so immens is their wealth; well,</l>
<l n="1063">the whole land of Persia is surrounded by great mountains,</l>
<l n="1064">covering a strip of land to the south from the Caspian Gates,</l>
<l n="1065">and extending even as far as the sea of the same name.</l>
<l n="1066">They inhabit it in three separate parts, some under the Bears</l>
<l n="1067">sit by the shade-giving mountains of the bow-carrying Medes;</l>
<l n="1068">some in the interior; and some to the south as far as the sea;</l>
<l n="1069">first, the Sabae, after them the Pasargadae, and nearby the Tasci,</l>
<l n="1070">and others who inhabit of the Persian land in two ways.</l>
<l n="1071">And many rivers make it fertile,</l>
<l n="1072">turning hither and thither in their winding flood-waters.</l>
<l n="1073">On one side is the great Coros, on the other the Choaspes,</l>
<l n="1074">drawing Indian water and flowing beside the land of the Susans.</l>
<l n="1075">On its banks you would see fair-eyed agate,</l>
<l n="1076">lying on the ground like cylinder, which from a rock</l>
<l n="1077">sweep down the torrents of the stormy river.</l>
<l n="1078">Moreover, continuously rejoicing in the warm wind,</l>
<l n="1079">fruits flourish closely packed against one another.</l>
<l n="1080">Now consider the remaining path of Asian land to the side of the sunrise:</l>
<l n="1081">for nearby the coastline of the continent comes to an end.</l>
<l n="1082">So, then, beside the Persian stream of the Ocean</l>
<l n="1083">the Carmanoi dwell under the rising sun,</l>
<l n="1084">not far from Persia, inhabiting the land in two sections:</l>
<l n="1085">the one group along the sea, the others dwellers of the interior mainland.</l>
<l n="1086">Towards the east of them extends the land of the Gedrosi,</l>
<l n="1087">neighbors to the yawning Ocean; to the side oft he sunrise of these</l>
<l n="1088">dwell the southern Scythoi near the Indus river,</l>
<l n="1089">which is opposite the Erythraean Sea,</l>
<l n="1090">very furiously driving a swift stream straight to the south,</l>
<l n="1091">beginning first from the windy Caucasus.</l>
<l n="1092">It has two mouths, and in the middle it runs past an island,</l>
<l n="1093">an island which the inhabitants call Patalene.</l>
<l n="1094">It divides the tribes of many people:</l>
<l n="1095">so, then, towards the setting sun</l>
<l n="1096">the Oreitae, and the Aribae, and the Arachotoi with linen mantles,</l>
<l n="1097">and the Satraidae, and all those beside the folds of Parpanisus,</l>
<l n="1098">all in common called by the name Arianoi,</l>
<l n="1099">who do not inhabit a lovely land, but one filled with fine</l>
<l n="1100">sand and rough with thickets;</l>
<l n="1101">but nevertheless, the means are sufficient for those living there,</l>
<l n="1102">for the earth provides a different unmixed blessing for them:</l>
<l n="1103">for in every direction there is the stone of red coral,</l>
<l n="1104">and in every direction veins under the rocks travail with a beautiful layer</l>
<l n="1105">of golden and dark blue lapis lazuli,</l>
<l n="1106">those who extract it bring in a life-supporting income.</l>
<l n="1107">Towards the side of the sunrise stretches the lovely land of the Indoi,</l>
<l n="1108">outermost of all, beside the edges of the Ocean,</l>
<l n="1109">the sun scorches it with its first rays</l>
<l n="1110">as it rises over the workings of the blessed ones and of men.</l>
<l n="1111">For this reason the inhabitants of the land are dark-skinned,</l>
<l n="1112">divinely sleek, and bear on their heads very thick hair</l>
<l n="1113">that resembles hyacinth;</l>
<l n="1114">some of them mine the sources of gold,</l>
<l n="1115">digging the sand with well-made mattocks;</l>
<l n="1116">some weave webs of linen; and others smooth</l>
<l n="1117">the silvery sawn-off tusks of elephants;</l>
<l n="1118">and others hunt on the jutting rocks of mountain-torrents,</l>
<l n="1119">either for the sea-green stone of beryl or sparkling</l>
<l n="1120">adamant or pale transparent jasper</l>
<l n="1121">or the gleaming stone of pure topaz</l>
<l n="1122">and sweet amethyst with its gentle purple color;</l>
<l n="1123">for the land fosters all sorts of wealth for men,</l>
<l n="1124">since it is irrigated here and there by ever-flowing rivers.</l>
<l n="1125">indeed, even the meadows always luxuriate with leaves;</l>
<l n="1126">for in one place millet prospers, and then in another place, in turn,</l>
<l n="1127">flourish forests of Erythraean reed.</l>
<l n="1128">Consider how I am to describe to you the shape and the rivers</l>
<l n="1129">and the windy mountains and the tribes of the land itself.</l>
<l n="1130">So, then, it is fixed on four sides,</l>
<l n="1131">all oblique, like the outline of a rhombus;</l>
<l n="1132">and the bordering Indus with its western waters</l>
<l n="1133">bounds the land, at the south the wave of the Erythraean Sea,</l>
<l n="1134">the Ganges to the side of the sunrise, the Caucasus to the pole of the Bears.</l>
<l n="1135">India inhabit many and prosperous men,</l>
<l n="1136">not dwelling all together with the same name, but separately</l>
<l n="1137">distinguished, near the immense Indus river</l>
<l n="1138">the Dardanees, where the Acesine, which flows crosswise from mounds,</l>
<l n="1139">is received by Hydaspes, navigable for ships.</l>
<l n="1140">After them also the silver-eddying Kophes follows third;</l>
<l n="1141">Amidst these rivers dwell the Sabae and the men Taxili,</l>
<l n="1142">and next the Scodri; thereupon follow the unspeakable tribes</l>
<l n="1143">of the Peucales; after them attendants of Dionysus,</l>
<l n="1144">the Gargaridae, dwell, where glittering product of gold</l>
<l n="1145">bear the Hypanis and the divine Magarsos,</l>
<l n="1146">most boisterous of rivers; from the mountain Emodus</l>
<l n="1147">arising they flow to the land of the Ganges,</l>
<l n="1148">which flows towards the south near the borders of the Colias land.</l>
<l n="1149">This, indeed, stoops to the deep-eddying Ocean,</l>
<l n="1150">steep and inaccessible to swift birds;</l>
<l n="1151">for this reason people call it "Aornis".</l>
<l n="1152">There is near the fair-flowing Ganges a wondrous</l>
<l n="1153">place, honored and sacred, which once Bacchus</l>
<l n="1154">in anger trampled, when the soft fawn-skins</l>
<l n="1155">of the Lenae were turned into shields, and in iron</l>
<l n="1156">suddenly were changed the thyrsi, and into the coils of serpents</l>
<l n="1157">the belts and the tendrils of the much-twisting vine,</l>
<l n="1158">at that time when in their folly they slighted the festival of the god.</l>
<l n="1159">For this reason they named it the Nysaean way,</l>
<l n="1160">and they duly established with their children all the rites.</l>
<l n="1161">And he himself, when he destroyed the tribes of dark Indoi,</l>
<l n="1162">ascended the Emodian mountains, under the foot of which</l>
<l n="1163">flows the great current of the eastern Ocean.</l>
<l n="1164">There he dragged two pillars somewhere near the boundaries of the earth,</l>
<l n="1165">and returned exulting to the stream of the Ismenus.</l>
<l n="1166">So many are the most notable men on the earth;</l>
<l n="1167">and others roam here and there over the continents</l>
<l n="1168">in their thousands, of whom no-one could intelligibly speak,</l>
<l n="1169">no mortal: only the gods can do all easily.</l>
<l n="1170">For they rounded off the first foundations,</l>
<l n="1171">and they proofed the deep channel of the measureless sea;</l>
<l n="1172">and they assigned all things for life,</l>
<l n="1173">distinguishing the stars, and they allotted to each</l>
<l n="1174">to have a share of the sea and the abundant mainland.</l>
<l n="1175">For this reason each land has obtained a different nature of configuration:</l>
<l n="1176">for one has been made white and shining,</l>
<l n="1177">and another darker, and yet another the appearance of both;</l>
<l n="1178">one is like the hue of Assyrian ochre,</l>
<l n="1179">and others are of different sorts; for thus great Zeus purposed.</l>
<l n="1180">Thus all things for humankind have been made diverse.</l>
<l n="1181">Farewell, you continents and islands in the sea,</l>
<l n="1182">and waters of Ocean and sacred streams of the sea,</l>
<l n="1183">and rivers, and springs, and wooded mountains.</l>
<l n="1184">For I have now run over the swell of the entire sea,</l>
<l n="1185">and the crooked path of the continents; so may I have</l>
<l n="1186">from the Blessed Ones themselves a recompense worthy of my hymns.</l>
</div>